{
  "reference_number": "13039",
  "clauses": [
    {
      "question": "1. What process should the Government use to set a new emissions reduction target in legislation?",
      "question_index": 0,
      "answer": "The Government sets a goal to reach net zero emissions by the second half of the century and the Climate Change Commission advises on the specific target for the Government to set later",
      "answer_index": 11,
      "notes": "NZ can provide an example of success to similarly developed countries. We can do this by achieving zero emissions by 2050 and\n then going even further."
    },
    {
      "question": "2. If the Government sets a 2050 target now, which is the best target for New Zealand?",
      "question_index": 1,
      "answer": "Net Zero Long-Lived Gases and Stabilised Short-Lived Gases - Long-lived gases to net zero by 2050 while also stabilising short-lived gases",
      "answer_index": 12,
      "notes": "The second option seems like a realistic goal and one that we may exceed. It will be important to achieve a realistic goal like this to\n build on success and help inspire other countries."
    },
    {
      "question": "3. How should New Zealand meet its targets?",
      "question_index": 2,
      "answer": "Domestic emissions reductions only (including from new forest planting)",
      "answer_index": 7,
      "notes": "NZ can better support the global movement by exemplifying progress, rather than by adding a drop in the bucket to support\n\n countries which are already exceeding certain targets. Investing in NZ rather than in other countries will also lead to greater economic\n returns in the medium to long term."
    },
    {
      "question": "4. Should the Zero Carbon Bill allow the 2050 target to be revised if circumstances change?",
      "question_index": 3,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": "The target should be locked in while we can, to prevent meddling by the sorts of highly conservative factions we have recently seen\n come to power in other countries."
    },
    {
      "question": "5. The Government proposes that three emissions budgets of five years each (i.e. covering the next 15 years) be in place at any given time. Do you agree with this proposal?",
      "question_index": 15,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Yes, staged targets will prevent us leaving a final target until the last moment. Staged targets will also help structure appropriate\n interventions."
    },
    {
      "question": "6. Should the Government be able to alter the last emissions budget (i.e. furthest into the future)?",
      "question_index": 4,
      "answer": "No - emissions budgets should not be able to be changed",
      "answer_index": 9,
      "notes": "For the same reason as #4."
    },
    {
      "question": "7. Should the Government have the ability to review and adjust the second emissions budget within a specific range under exceptional circumstances? See p36 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 5,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Yes, because this may include an opportunity to be even more ambitious. Likewise, it seems best to keep all targets achievable,\n\ngiven circumstances which may include another major disaster or financial crisis."
    },
    {
      "question": "8. Do you agree with the considerations we propose that the Government and the Climate Change Commission take into account when advising on and setting budgets? See p44 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 6,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": "I agree, except that the term \"fuel poverty\" is problematic. This term should be replaced with the concept of energy poverty where\n\npossible, to recognise the increasing viability of electric energy over combustible fuels."
    },
    {
      "question": "9. Should the Zero Carbon Bill require Governments to set out plans within a certain timeframe to achieve the emissions budgets?",
      "question_index": 7,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Yes, science and moral ethics dictate that this bill should obligate future governments, regardless of the ideology of the day."
    },
    {
      "question": "10. What are the most important issues for the Government to consider in setting plans to meet budgets? For example, who do we need to work with, what else needs to be considered?",
      "question_index": 8,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "All plans need to result from consultation with distinct geographic area because carbon-producing activity varies so much throughout\n\nNew Zealand. This will also enable consultation with applicable iwi."
    },
    {
      "question": "11. The Government has proposed that the Climate Change Commission advises on and monitors New Zealand's progress towards its goals. Do you agree with these functions? See p42 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 9,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Yes, these goals need to be monitored with a high degree of independence and the heft to make sure that results will influence\nimportant decisions."
    },
    {
      "question": "12. What role do you think the Climate Change Commission should have in relation to the New Zealand Emissions Trading Scheme (NZ ETS)?",
      "question_index": 10,
      "answer": "Advising the Government on policy settings in the NZ ETS",
      "answer_index": 6,
      "notes": "Unless the Commission is somehow composed of elected representatives, it will difficult to justify their decisions as part of a\n\ndemocracy."
    },
    {
      "question": "13. The Government has proposed that Climate Change Commissioners need to have a range of essential and desirable expertise. Do you agree with the proposed expertise? See p45 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 11,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "The many scientific, technological, social, cultural and other aspects of climate change make this an essential part of interpreting\nrelevant information. This position is discussed in further detail in the paper written by Huggins et al. and attached to this submission."
    },
    {
      "question": "14. Do you think the Zero Carbon Bill should cover adapting to climate change?",
      "question_index": 12,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "There are too many aspects of climate change that have not been mitigated in time, including sea level rise and sea temperatures."
    },
    {
      "question": "15. The Government has proposed a number of new functions to help us adapt to climate change. Do you agree with the proposed functions? See p47 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 13,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "16. Should we explore setting up a targeted adaptation reporting power that could see some organisations share information on their exposure to climate change risks?",
      "question_index": 14,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "This should be an important part of reporting by organisations in both the public and private sector."
    },
    {
      "question": "Do you have any other comments you'd like to make?",
      "question_index": 16,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "Most of the people making these submissions will not be directly affected by the most threatening impacts of climate change. The\n\nright actions, taken within our lifetimes, can still ensure that future generations of New Zealanders will not live to see many of those\nimpacts."
    }
  ]
}
